Register of the Maerose J. Evans papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Maerose J. Evans papers
1965-1994
1969-1975
95049
Hoover Institution Archives
13 manuscript boxes (5.2 linear feet)
Correspondence, minutes, reports, financial records, bulletins, newsletters, serial issues, clippings, and photographs relating to efforts to secure the release of American prisoners of war in Vietnam, efforts to secure information on American servicemen reported missing in action, and the families of those servicemen.
Evans, Maerose J.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1995.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Maerose J. Evans, originally from New Jersey, was the wife of Commander James J. Evans, United States Navy. Commander Evans was a naval aviator whose aircraft was lost during a reconnaissance mission over Laos in 1965. In 1974 he was presumed killed in action, and in 1977 his remains were positively identified and returned. At the time of his disappearance, the couple was living in Alameda, California, with their two children, Monica and James.
Maerose Evans was involved with the National League of Families of American Prisoners and Missing in Southeast Asia during its founding and incorporation in 1969 and 1970. She eventually became the Western Regional coordinator, which oversaw chapters in California, Oregon, Washington, Arizona, Nevada, Colorado, Wyoming, Utah, New Mexico, Idaho, Montana, Alaska, and Hawaii. She was heavily involved in the Prisoner of War/Missing in Action issue in the United States and gave many speeches and talks about the inhumane treatment of prisoners and the need for a full accounting of the missing men. Evans even travelled to Laos in 1972 in an attempt to gain more information about her missing husband. Eventually, she left the position of Regional Coordinator and the National League of Families over a disagreement about the direction of the organization, and she believed that her values no longer aligned with those of the League.
In 1984, Evans married George Humphreys, whom she remained with until her death in 1995. She was buried in Arlington National Cemetery next to her first husband, Commander Evans.
Scope and Content of Collection
Correspondence, minutes, reports, financial records, bulletins, and newsletters from the National League of Families, supporting committees, and the Prisoner of War/Missing in Action League of Santa Clara County. The majority of the collection is made up of personal correspondence related to efforts to secure the release of American prisoners of war in Vietnam, efforts to secure information on American servicemen reported missing in action, and the families of those servicemen. A small amount of serial issues, clippings, and photographs related to the POW/MIA issue are also included.
Most of the materials focus on the Western Region or California families of servicemen who were prisoners of war or missing in action. There is also some focus on the issue at a national and international level.
National League of Families of American Prisoners and Missing in Southeast Asia.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975--Prisoners and prisons, North Vietnamese.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975--Missing in action.; Prisoners of war.; United States--Armed Forces.; Navy spouses.
- Correspondence, 1965-1989
  Scope and Contents note
  Correspondence between Maerose Evans and various others, organized alphabetically by organization or correspondent's last name. When possible, the original order of the creator was maintained.
  - A, 1972-1976 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - B, 1972-1977 (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - C, 1971-1976 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - Canaan, G. C., 1971-1974 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Change of Command invitations, 1965-1973 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Christmas cards, 1967-1972 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Clum, Sadie, 1973-1976 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Colgan, Jack, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Correspondence from bracelet wearers, 1972-1976 (Box-folder 1: 9)
    POW/MIA bracelets were first created in May 1970 by the group Voices in Vital America (VIVA). They sold for $2.50 or $3.00 and were engraved with the rank, name, and loss date of an American serviceman who was captured or went missing during the Vietnam War.
  - Cranston, Alan, 1972-1975 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - D, 1972-1978 (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - E, 1972-1975 (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - F, 1972-1976 (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - Families for Immediate Release, 1972 (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - G, 1972-1976 (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - Goldsmith, John A., 1976-1978 (Box-folder 2: 7)
  - Gratch, Archie William, 1972-1979 (Box-folder 2: 8-9)
  - H, 1971-1977 (Box-folder 2: 10)
  - Hillman, Jo, 1973-1974 (Box-folder 2: 11)
  - I, 1974-1975 (Box-folder 2: 12)
  - J, 1972-1975 (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - K, 1972-1977 (Box-folder 3: 2)
  - Ketchum, William M., 1974 (Box-folder 3: 3)
  - L, 1972-1977 (Box-folder 3: 4)
  - Lawson, Richard L., 1974-1975 (Box-folder 3: 5)
  - M, 1971-1989 (Box-folder 3: 6)
  - Mauldin, Dick, 1971-1976 (Box-folder 3: 7)
  - McCloskey, Paul, 1976-1978 (Box-folder 3: 8)
  - Miscellaneous, 1972-1974 (Box-folder 3: 9)
    Correspondence that was written and sent to people other than the creator and not related to any of the organizations represented in the collection.
  - N, 1972-1976 (Box-folder 3: 10)
  - United States Department of the Navy, 1968-1973 (Box-folder 3: 11)
  - O, 1972-1974 (Box-folder 3: 12)
  - P, 1971-1976 (Box-folder 3: 13)
  - Percy, Charles H., 1973-1975 (Box-folder 3: 14)
  - Pursell, Dan, 1969-1973 (Box-folder 3: 15)
  - Q, 1974 (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - R, 1971-1977 (Box-folder 4: 2)
  - S, 1971-1975 (Box-folder 4: 3)
  - Schlesinger, James, 1974 (Box-folder 4: 4)
  - Scott, James H., 1971-1974 (Box-folder 4: 5)
  - Shields, Roger, 1972-1976 (Box-folder 4: 6)
  - Sieverts, Frank, 1973-1975 (Box-folder 4: 7)
  - Smith, Bernice, 1974-1977 (Box-folder 4: 8)
  - Stark, Pete, 1973-1977 (Box-folder 4: 9)
  - Stratton, Richard A., 1974-1979 (Box-folder 4: 10)
  - T, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 4: 11)
  - Tenoso, Ed and Kathy, 1972 (Box-folder 4: 12)
  - Thorsness, Leo, 1974 (Box-folder 4: 13)
  - V, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 4: 14)
  - W, 1972-1975 (Box-folder 4: 15)
  - Williams, Jerry A., 1972-1974 (Box-folder 4: 16)
  - Y, 1975 (Box-folder 4: 17)
  - Z, 1976 (Box-folder 4: 18)
  - Zacharies, J. M., 1972-1975 (Box-folder 4: 19)
  - Zumwalt, E. R., 1970-1973 (Box-folder 4: 20)
- National League of Prisoners of War/Missing in Action Families File, 1969-1976
  Contains correspondence, meeting minutes, mailings and promotional material, printed matter, and organizational documents for the National League of Families of Prisoners of War/Missing in Action (NLF) during its founding and early years. There is more emphasis on the Western Region and California state chapter than any other part of the organization.
  The NLF is an organization that was formed in the late 1960s and formally incorporated in 1970. Membership was for family or close relatives of military personnel that were listed as a prisoner of war (POW) or missing in action (MIA). The organization was headed by a National Board of Directors and divided into four regions, each headed by a Regional Coordinator. Each state within the region elected a State Coordinator that worked with the Regional Coordinator and Board of Directors to raise awareness about the POW/MIA issue in America.
  The NLF believed that the American government was too complacent in its negotiations for the humane treatment and release of POWs during the Vietnam War. Indochinese countries were accused of violating the Geneva Convention by not issuing a complete list of POWs captured, not providing adequate food or medical treatment, refusing to allow the Red Cross to inspect POW camps, and not allowing mail to reach POWs. The NLF was organized to raise awareness of these issues and pressure both the American government and foreign governments to account for the missing men.
  - Correspondence, 1970-1974
    Correspondence related to the functions of the National League of Families (NLF). Letters sent and received are between or on behalf of members of the governing board of NLF. Coordinator and Regional letters are between the numerous State and Region Coordinators.
    - Regional letters, 1971-1973 (Box-folder 5: 1)
    - Letters sent, 1971-1974 (Box-folder 5: 2)
    - Letters received, 1971-1974 (Box-folder 5: 3)
    - Coordinator letters, 1970-1974 (Box-folder 5: 4)
  - Newsletters, 1973-1976 (Box-folder 5: 5)
  - Western Coordinator expenses, 1971-1974 (Box-folder 5: 6)
  - Member mailings, 1970-1974 (Box-folder 5: 7)
  - National conventions, 1971-1973 (Box-folder 5: 8)
  - Special reports and league mailings, 1969-1974 (Box-folder 5: 9)
  - Board meetings file, 1971-1974
    Meeting minutes, agendas, and special reports prepared for the Board of Directors meetings of the National League of Families.
    - 1971 May (Box-folder 5: 10)
    - 1972
      - January (Box-folder 5: 11)
      - March (Box-folder 5: 12)
      - October (Box-folder 5: 13)
      - November (Box-folder 5: 14)
    - 1973
      - January (Box-folder 5: 15)
      - February (Box-folder 6: 1)
      - June (Box-folder 6: 2)
      - July (Box-folder 6: 3)
      - August (Box-folder 6: 4)
      - October (Box-folder 6: 5)
      - December (Box-folder 6: 6)
    - 1974
      - February (Box-folder 6: 7)
      - March (Box-folder 6: 8)
      - April (Box-folder 6: 9)
      - June (Box-folder 6: 10)
      - August (Box-folder 6: 11)
  - Promotional material, 1970-1975 (Box-folder 6: 12)
  - House of Representatives Bill 16520, 1974 (Box-folder 6: 13)
  - Support Our Prisoners of War campaign, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 6: 14)
  - Western Region, 1971-1974 (Box-folder 6: 15)
  - State folders file, 1971-1975
    Materials related to the various state chapters of the National League of Families.
    - Alaska, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 6: 16)
    - Arizona, 1971-1973 (Box-folder 6: 17)
    - Colorado, 1973-1975 (Box-folder 6: 18)
    - Northern California, 1970-1974 (Box-folder 7: 1)
    - Southern California, 1971-1974 (Box-folder 7: 2)
    - Connecticut, 1974 (Box-folder 7: 3)
    - Hawaii, 1973 (Box-folder 7: 4)
    - Idaho, 1972-1974 (Box-folder 7: 5)
    - Maryland, 1972-1974 (Box-folder 7: 6)
    - Mississippi, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 7: 7)
    - Montana, 1971-1973 (Box-folder 7: 8)
    - Nevada, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 7: 9)
    - Ohio, 1970-1975 (Box-folder 7: 10)
    - Oregon, 1973-1975 (Box-folder 7: 11)
    - Utah, 1971-1974 (Box-folder 7: 12)
    - Virginia, 1972 (Box-folder 7: 13)
    - Washington, 1971-1975 (Box-folder 7: 14)
    - Wyoming, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 7: 15)
    - West Virginia, 1973 (Box-folder 7: 16)
  - Printed matter, 1971-1974 (Box-folder 7: 17)
    Informational brochures and pamphlets of Freedom Tree dedications and luncheons.
- Committees File, 1972-1974
  Contains materials from different committees and groups that were involved with the POW/MIA issue and with the National League of Families.
  - Forgotten Americans Committee of Kansas, 1972-1974 (Box-folder 7: 18)
  - Forgotten Americans Committee, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 7: 19)
  - Voices in Vital America, 1972-1974 (Box-folder 8: 1-2)
  - Freedom Tree Dedication, 1972-1974 (Box-folder 8: 3)
  - Concern for Prisoners of War, 1972 (Box-folder 8: 4)
  - Repatriation, Rehabilitation, and Readjustment Committee, 1972 (Box-folder 8: 5)
  - Northern California Peace Action Coalition, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 8: 6)
  - Committee of Liaison with Families of Servicemen Detained in North Vietnam, 1973 (Box-folder 8: 7)
  - Remember the Pueblo Committee, 1973 (Box-folder 8: 8)
  - Americans Who Care, 1973 (Box-folder 8: 9)
  - Dallas Cares, 1974 (Box-folder 8: 10)
  - Help Hospitalized Veterans, 1973 (Box-folder 8: 11)
- Prisoners of War/Missing in Action League of Santa Clara File, 1970-1975
  The Prisoners of War/Missing in Action (POW/MIA) League of Santa Clara County is a now defunct organization with similar goals as the National League of Families. They represented the servicemen of Santa Clara County who were POW/MIA. The organization sold POW/MIA bracelets, sponsored a letter writing campaign, hosted talks and support groups, and coordinated with the National League of Families on events. Their two goals were to get all American POWs released and to get a full accounting of all the MIA servicemen. By the time the organization closed in 1974 they believed only the first goal had been completed.
  - Correspondence, 1971-1974 (Box-folder 9: 1-3)
  - Board meeting minutes, 1971-1974 (Box-folder 9: 4)
  - Newsletters, 1970-1975 (Box-folder 9: 5)
  - Mailings, 1971-1973 (Box-folder 9: 6)
  - Presidio Action League, 1973 (Box-folder 9: 7)
  - Prisoners of War/Missing in Action International, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 9: 8)
  - Poster, undated (Box-folder 9: 9)
- Subject File, 1970-1974
  - City proclamations, 1970 (Box-folder 10: 1)
    Official proclamations from various American cities that call for the accounting of missing men and humane treatment of prisoners of war.
  - Congress, 1969-1975 (Box-folder 10: 2)
    A small number of Congressional publications and reports related to the POW/MIA issue.
  - Evans, James J., 1965-1977 (Box-folder 10: 3)
    Documents related to Commander James J. Evans, who went missing in action in 1965. Includes a copy of the telegram sent to his wife informing her of his status.
  - Laos meeting, 1973 (Box-folder 10: 3)
    Transcript, clippings, and written report on a meeting in Laos with members of the National League of Families and a Laos official.
  - Military social events, 1969-1972 (Box-folder 10: 5-6)
    Invitations and announcements to lunches and other social events at military bases in Northern California.
  - Peace movements, 1971 (Box-folder 10: 7)
    Materials related to American citizen peace efforts in order to stop the war in Vietnam.
  - Prisoners of War/Missing in Action, 1970-1974 (Box-folder 10: 8-10)
    Materials related to the Prisoner of War/Missing in Action movement in the United States but not directly related to the National League of Families or the POW/MIA League of Santa Clara County.
  - United States Department of Defense, 1971-1973 (Box-folder 11: 1)
    Publications and statistic sheets produced by the Department of Defense about American servicemen that were prisoners of war or missing in action.
- Photographs, 1966-1972
  Photographs of prisoners of war and the conditions they were kept in, a photo contact sheet and altered photo from the Navy Times, and photographs from Family Day at the Naval Air Station in Alameda, California.
  - Prisoners of war, 1966-1970 (Box-folder 11: 2)
    Photographs include Lieutenant Commander H. A. Stafford, Lieutenant Commander John S. McCain, Lieutenant James J. Connell, Lieutenant D. G. Rehman, D. B. Hegdahl, Captain M. N. Jones, Lieutenant Robert F. Frishman, and Lieutenant Colonel J. L. Hughes as prisoners of war. Folder also contains four negatives and two slides.
  - General, 1969 (Box-folder 11: 3)
    Two images of unidentified servicemen, one image of an unidentified group of people, an image with accompanying letter from an Open House at the California Air Station in 1969, and a photohraph of a political cartoon with accompanying letter from 1974.
  - Navy Times, 1972 April 2 (Box-folder 11: 4)
  - Family Day, undated (Box-folder 11: 5)
    Six photographs from a Family day at the Naval Air Station in Alameda, California. The photographs are undated but most likely between the years of 1968 and 1977.
- Printed Matter, 1965-1994
  The bulk of the series is comprised of pamphlets related to the Prisoner of War/Missing in Action issue and the conflict in Southeast Asia from 1960 through 1975. Additionally, there are a few periodicals and unpublished fact sheets.
  - Clippings, 1969-1994
    Contains newspaper clippings collected by the creator. Original folder titles have been retained when possible, and loose clippings were put into a general folder. Arranged alphabetically following the general folder.
    - General, 1970-1994 (Box-folder 11: 6-9)
    - 1990 (Box-folder 12: 1)
    - 1993 (Box-folder 12: 2)
    - Bracelets, 1971-1973 (Box-folder 12: 3)
    - Laos, 1972-1982 (Box-folder 12: 4)
    - Lockhart, 1969-1970 (Box-folder 12: 5-6)
    - McGovern, 1972 (Box-folder 12: 7)
    - Missing in action, 1973-1982 (Box-folder 12: 8)
    - Prisoners of war, 1971-1982 (Box-folder 12: 9-10)
    - United States and Nixon, 1972-1981 (Box-folder 12: 11)
    - Vietnam, 1972-1982 (Box-folder 13: 1-2)
    - Wives and families, 1972-1981 (Box-folder 13: 3)
  - Air Force and Space Digest, 1969-1970 (Box-folder 13: 4)
  - Cal-Vet Newsletter, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 13: 5)
  - Newsweek, 1973 February 26 (Box-folder 13: 6)
  - In Brief for the P.O.W.: A Catch-Up on News from Missing Years, 1965-1972 (Box-folder 13: 7)
  - Commanders Digest, 1972-1974 (Box-folder 13: 8)
  - Navy Wifeline, 1971 Fall (Box-folder 13: 9)
  - Ladycom, 1973 February (Box-folder 13: 10)
  - The Oak Leaf, 1973 February 23 (Box-folder 13: 11)
  - Medical Service Digest, 1973 November (Box-folder 13: 12)
  - Missing in Action, Prisoner of War: A Primer, 1971 (Box-folder 13: 13)
  - Hanoi, Release the Prisoners, 1971-1972 (Box-folder 13: 14)
  - Aerospace Speech Series: Prisoner of War/Missing in Action, 1971 September (Box-folder 13: 15)
  - Snapshots of Life of Captured United States Pilots in the Detention Camps of the Democratic Republic of Vietnam, 1969-1974 (Box-folder 13: 16)
  - Prisoner of War/Missing in Action fact sheets, 1970-1972 (Box-folder 13: 17)
  - Department of Defense Information Pamphlet for Families of United States Servicemen Who Are Prisoners of War or Are Missing in Action in Southeast Asia, 1972 September 22 (Box-folder 13: 18)
  - Miscellaneous, 1969-1973 (Box-folder 13: 19)
    Four pamphlets not related to POWs or MIAs. The titles include the Fremont Rotary Opinion from 17 January 1973, If You Want Air Time: A Handbook for Publicity Chairmen, Alameda Meals-On-Wheels, and How to Display and Respect the Flag of the United States.
  - Gist: A Quick Reference Aid on United States Foreign Relations Primarily for Government Use, 1971 September (Box-folder 13: 20)
  - Citizens Prisoner of War and Missing in Action Assistance Program, 1970 March (Box-folder 13: 21)
  - In the Name of Humanity...Write On!, 1971 March (Box-folder 13: 22)
  - Birth of a Cause: Colorado Springs and the American Prisoner of War, 1970-1973 (Box-folder 13: 23)
  - Ten Myths About Vietnam, 1969 December (Box-folder 13: 24)
  - Legislative Guide for the Military, 1971 January (Box-folder 13: 25)
  - National Guard Association of the United States: 24th Annual Conference, 1972 September (Box-folder 13: 26)